Nishant A Jalan Android Developer & Tutor

LinkedIn Portfolio GitHub

I am a programming enthusiast who started his journey learning Java when he was 11 years old. Hooked onto programming, I expanded my knowledge from Android development to Full Stack Development, alongside tutoring the basics of programming to junior programmers entering this field. **Areas of expertise:** Kotlin, Android, Java, JavaScript, Front-end development with React, Vue and Svelte along with Bootstrap and Vuetify, Back-end development with Node and Express. **Achievements:** Oracle Certified Java Professional.

PROJECTS

Pictionary January 2022 — Ongoing

- The application will allow multiple users to join a single room with their names and one-by-one, each player will be presented three random words to choose from and he/she would draw on a Canvas to illustrate the word for the other players to guess.
- Frontend is undergoing development in Android/Kotlin with Clean Architecture + MVVM and Jetpack Compose. Backend has reached production level, built with Node and Express.js and Socket.io hosted on a free public server.
- Used modern programming paradigms such as Dependency Injection with Dagger Hilt, Http Requests with Ktor-client, WebSocket connection with Socket.io-client. Flows and Coroutines with Jetpack Compose Navigation.

Project Manager July 2021 — August 2021

- A simple project built with Vue.js and Firebase Authentication and Firestore for users to manage their project deadlines.
- Used Vuetify component library with Vue 2 for incorporating Material UI Design and aesthetic components.

Current Affairs March 2021

- Created a News Application with MVVM Architecture and Dagger Hilt Dependency Injection along with Retrofit2 calls to a REST API.
- Used Navigation Jetpack Component with LiveData to observe over changes made and Custom Pagination for RecyclerView to display all the news.
- · Added a feature of selecting favorite news and saving them to Room Persistent Library to display in a Fragment.

WhatsApp Clone February 2020 — April 2020

- Created a simple chat application with Kotlin and Firebase and listen to realtime updates.
- Learnt the complex techniques used in RecyclerView to display custom layouts and uploading images and files to the Firebase Storage.

Chess March 2019 — May 2019

- · My first major android application.
- Used the basic navigation through activities and UI updates and business logic for finding available moves and detecting checks.

EXPERIENCE

Software Engineering Intern

March 2022 — Ongoing

October 2021 — December 2021

LearnApp

Noida, Remote

Developing components required for the Edtech Android application in Kotlin.

Junior Android Developer

ALMINDS Pvt Ltd Kolkata

- Developed an Android Application in Kotlin using MVVM + Clean Architecture and Data Binding.
- Properly integrating modern programming paradigms: Dependency Injection (Dagger Hilt), Room DB, Flows (Coroutines), Retrofit, ViewModel and LiveData.
- Coded numerous Custom Views to match the complex UI design with UX animations.

Full Stack Intern June 2021 — September 2021

DoubtConnect

Remote

- Started my role as an Android Intern, but switched over to completing the web application using React.js and debugging server bugs and creating an Admin Dashboard website with the new Svelte.js framework connected with the back-end Express.js.
- Developed an android application in a team with Kotlin. Initiating network calls and updating Firebase database, creating custom components for the UI and debugging errors.

Technical Director August 2020 — October 2020

X-Uberance '20 Virtual Fest Kolkata

- X-Uberance'20 is the annual virtual fest in my high school. I developed the Android Mobile Application for this fest, managed the website and graphic team, and reported directly to the President.
- The Application was connected to Firebase Services Authentication and Cloud Firestore. The Application was informative, detailing the events, timings, rules and regulations. The Representatives of each school could register their participants, submit their videos for certain events and Bet to gain virtual points.

Java Head Teacher June 2020 — December 2020

Code The Universe Remote

- Designed the course curriculum and structure and managed the other Java Teachers.
- · Taught Core Java in real-time to newbie programmers across the globe on Discord. Assigned and corrected homework and answered doubts students raised in their projects and assignments elsewhere.

EDUCATION

General Science with C.Sc., St. Xavier's Collegiate School, ISC: 96.0%

May 2017 — June 2021

VOLUNTEERING

CS and Math Teacher December 2021 — Present Schoolhouse.world

Remote

- Host Live Help Sessions for an hour three times a week.
- Help learners in programming and mathematics based on specific requests.
- Conducting a series for learners to prepare for the SAT Math for the March test.
- Hosting a series for learners to prepare for the AP Computer Science A in May 2022.
- Hosted a 2-month course to teach Kotlin.

Session Auditor January 2022 — Present

Schoolhouse.world Remote

 I audit other tutor's sessions to check for policy violations and provide feedback on tutor's mastery, engagement and environment that they create in the meetings.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming Skills Android, React.js, Vue.js, Node.js, MongoDB, Bootstrap, JQuery

Some Other Skills Teamwork, Teaching/Mentoring, Collaboration, Piano

Programming/Scripting Java, Kotlin, JavaScript, TypeScript

AWARDS & HONORS

2019 Oracle Certified Java Associate; Oracle Certified Java Professional; First in National Coding Competition

2021 The Harmonised Melody Cup